this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
c-radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Vijay shamanat and today
my guest is vladislav yukas Vlad is the
head of r d at Siemens health insurance
team played digital Health platform and
reliability lead for all of Siemens
healthy news digital Health Products
Vlad is also the author of the book
establishing SRE foundation's a
step-by-step guide to introducing site
reliability engineering and software
delivery organizations Vlad welcome to
software engineering radio is there
anything I missed in your bio that you
would like to add thank you very much
brijesh for inviting me and for
introducing me I think you've covered
everything so looking forward to getting
started with the episode great we have
covered SRE previously in SE radio in
episode 548 where Alex discussed
implementing service level objectives
episode 544 where Ganesh discussed the
differences between devops and SRE
episode 455 where Jaime talked about
software Telemetry and episode 276 where
Beyond top about site reliability
engineering as a subject in this episode
we will talk about the foundations of
implementing SRE within an organization
and I'll also make sure that we'll link
back to all those previous episodes in
the show notes
to start off flat can you give me a
brief introduction on what SRE is and
how it differs from traditional Ops
let me start by giving you a little bit
of history of SRE SRE is a methodology
that called site reliability engineering
and it was conceived at Google because
Google has a big problem many years ago
which was Google was growing and the
number of people that was required to
operate Google also was growing
and the problem was that Google was
growing so fast that it became
impossible to hire the operations
engineer in line with the growth of
Google
and they were looking for solutions to
that problem how can you grow a web
property in such a way that you don't
require a linear growth of operation
Personnel in order to run the site
and that led to the birth of SRE
approaches which they then several years
later wrote up in the well-known SRE
books by Google and this is where it's
coming from so it got its origins in a
way of setting up operations in such a
way that you can grow the the site the
web property and at the same time you
don't need to grow linearly the
Personnel that's required to run it so
it's got a very business oriented
approach and digging deeper it's got its
origins in software engineering at
Google there is a saying that SRE is
what happens when you task software
Engineers with designing the operations
function of the Enterprise and it's true
so you once you dig into this you see
this software engineering approach
inside SRE how it's different from the
traditional way of operating software is
that it's got
a set of Primitives that enable you to
create good alignment of the
organization on operational concerns
because it gives the participants in a
software delivery organization clear
roles to fulfill
and using that then the alignment can be
brought about if an organization is
serious about implementing SRE and once
that alignment is there then it's
possible to do the alerting of the
operations Engineers not just on the
traditional I.T parameters like for
example CPU is too high or the memory is
too low but you actually are able to
alert on the symptoms that are really
experienced by the users so you are
alerting on the higher level stuff so to
speak that's really felt by the user and
once you do this then also the alerts
they are much more meaningful to the
operations Engineers running this site
because then there is a clear connection
between the alert and the user
experience and with that the motivation
to fix the problem is high and also you
don't get as many problems you don't get
as many alerts as you would if you just
alert on the it parameters like CPU
usage is too high and things like that I
like the code when you say sorry is what
happens when you get software Engineers
to design operations and run it and I
believe that also implies that software
Engineers will implement the software
engineer design principles like
continuous integration and engineering
principles around measurability yeah so
in terms of software engineering
approach in SRE fundamentally SRE brings
to the table is Imagine you've got a
software engineering team and that's
also engineering team is ready to ship
some digital service into production
and and typically they just do it and
then they see what happens with SRE
that's not the approach that the team
would take with SRE before doing the
final deployment the team will get
together including the product owner and
they will Define the so-called service
level objectives for this service
and these service level objectives they
would then quantify the reliability of
the service the reliability that they
want the service to fulfill and then
once deployed to production that
reliability which is Quantified will get
monitored and then they will get alerts
on whenever they don't fulfill their
liability as envisioned so you see it
creates a very powerful feedback loop
where you apply effectively the tried
and true scientific method to software
operations so you before you deploy to
production you then Define the slos
which quantify the reliability that you
want your service to provide and then
once the service is in production then
you get feedback from production that
tells you whenever you don't fulfill the
reliability that you actually thought
the service would provide so it provides
that powerful additional feedback loop
which is actually pretty tight and that
means that you don't just do continuous
integration in a sense that you've got
some stages some stages that lead you
through some testing towards production
but you also think about the operational
aspects much more during the development
because there is an ongoing conversation
about the quantification of reliability
we will dig a bit deeper into slos how
do you you know go and educate the teams
about it and how do you implement it
later in the podcast but prior to that I
wanted to understand a bit about you
know prior to SRE organizations used
methodologies like ITIL Information
Technology infrastructure library and
some organizations still continue to use
that this SRE complementary to ITIL or
is it something which will replace itl
right RTL is a very very popular
methodology to set up the it function of
an Enterprise I think there is a bit of
misconception there in the industry on
the one hand ITIL is there to as the
name suggests set up the it function of
an Enterprise so every Enterprise
requires an ID function in order to set
up the shared services that are used by
all the Departments and that's what ITIL
is great for
whereas SRE has got a different focus
and therefore it also complementary to
ITIL so sres focus is to
put a software delivery organization in
a position to operate the digital
services at scale so it's not about
setting up an I.T function of an
Enterprise it's about really be able to
operate highly scalable Digital Services
that the company offers as a product so
therefore the existence of ITIL and SRE
in an Enterprise is very complementary
so there is actually no contradiction
there but you are totally right in
noticing that actually in the industry
these things they are often not clearly
delineated which leads to questions okay
so do we now do SRE or do we now do ITIL
and if we now do idle do we need to
throw it overboard and replace it with
SRE because these are two different
methodologies which you've got totally
different Focus well not totally
different Focus but I would say a rather
different Focus so these questions they
actually don't need to arise because
those two methodologies are
complementary so one thing is with ITIL
you set up your it function in such a
way that everything is compliant that
you provide good quality of service to
the Enterprise users and with SRE you
create a powerful alignment on
operational concerns within the software
delivery organization that also operates
the services that you offer right so if
I understood it correctly I tell us
broader in scope it's about introducing
the entire IIT function and setting up
that environment whereas SRE is focused
on addressing the concern about
reliability is that a right
understanding yes in general that's the
right understanding that's right okay
appreciate you know Google introduced
SRE as a concept based on their journey
of setting it up it was very new to the
industry and since then many
organizations have you know introduced
SRE into into their own way of operating
and setting up operations can you tell
me the common pitfalls or challenges
that organizations have encountered
while introducing SRE in the existing
setup
definitely thanks for this question
because that's exactly the question that
I was answering at length while I was
writing my book establishing SRE
foundations the central question of the
book was okay so you've got some
examples of SRE implementation at
companies like Google where it
originated and those are the companies
that were born on the internet and
therefore they were looking for new
approaches to operate highly scalable
Digital Services and now you've got some
traditional organization and you want to
also introduce something like SRE
because you think it might help you with
the operations of your Digital Services
but you've got a totally different
context you've got a totally different
context from the organizational point of
view from the people point of view from
the technical point of view from the
culture point of view from the process
point of view so everything is different
now
would it be possible to take say SRE out
of Google and implant it into another
organization and would would it start
blossoming or not
and the main challenges there
I would say are a couple
which are with SRE you've got some
responsibilities that are typically not
there in a traditional software delivery
Organization for example in a
traditional software delivery
organization the developers they never
go on call developers just develop and
as you mentioned with the example of
continuous integration there
tasks and with the final internal
environment so to speak from then
onwards then someone else takes the
software and brings it into production
whatever it is whether it's on premise
or say some data center or Cloud
deployment and so on so with SRE
developers they need to start going on
call for their services the extent to
which they go on call is a matter of
negotiation so they could either go on
call completely so being fully uncalled
fully responsible for their services or
it could be just a small percentage of
their time but in any case developers
they need to go on call that's a huge
change
and that means that developers need to
start acting like traditional operations
Engineers whereas on the other side on
the side of the operations
they are used to operate services so
they are used to being on call whereas
what they need to do Under the SRE
framework they need to enable developers
to go on call and that's a totally new
thing to them because they suddenly need
to become software developers developing
a framework developing an infrastructure
that enables others to do operations
and that's a very big change because
then in essence the development
department needs to do operations work
and the operations department needs to
do development work and that's a
difficult transformation do you have any
stories around how developers within
your organization
took these ask about you know getting
involved in operations and being on call
how was their reaction and how did you
approach that negotiation
yes definitely thanks for asking that
question I think that'll be a very
interesting one to answer and hopefully
also to listen to when we started with
the Siemens health and year team play
digital Health platform we the first
ones in the company to offer software as
a service so we were the first ones in
the company to put up a service out
there it was in the cloud oh it is in
the cloud and then
offer that as an offering on a
subscription basis so before that the
company didn't sell subscriptions and
with the team play digital Health
platform we started selling
subscriptions so with the sell of
subscriptions came also the realization
that now the obligation of running the
services is actually on us
and with that then came the realization
that we need to learn how to operate the
services and the services are deployed
in six data centers around the world and
there was also a growing number of users
and with that of course the expectations
of the availability of the service were
growing higher and higher with the
higher expectations of availability of
the service also the realization came in
that that leads to shorter and shorter
time to recover from the incidents that
might happen and with that then came the
realization that in order to be able to
recover from incidents fast we need
totally new processes which we didn't
have back then so we need the developers
to be very close to production only then
it's possible to recover fast from the
incidents and we need to equip the
Developers
first of all with some technical
infrastructure for being able to do so
then also with some processes and with
some mindset change because that's a
totally new area for them
so once that realization set in within
started looking for Solutions and after
stumbling a couple of times we then
arrived at SRE we then started learning
about a series so what that means how
that could work could that work in our
context and then we decided to give it a
try at some point so we then decided to
start building a very small piece of
infrastructure inside the operations
organization so we put a real developer
inside the operations organization who
then started digging deep by into the
SRE Concepts and implementing them for
our organization and then we started
going team by team so then essentially
traversing the organization onboarding
them onto the infrastructure and doing
this in a very agile manner which means
the the infrastructure was always no
more than one step ahead of the teams
that were using the infrastructure that
means that the feedback loop between a
feature implemented in the
infrastructure and the and that feature
being used by one of the teams was very
tight which drove them the further
development of the infrastructure so we
made sure that any feature that we
Implement gets used by by the teams in
the daily operations very quickly with
that we get either the confirmation that
the features implemented properly or we
get feedback how to adapt the feature to
meet the need of a particular team
better so that was our approach and over
time we managed to implant the SRE ideas
in all teams until the points came where
as Harry became the default methodology
of running services in the organization
I'd like to dig a bit deeper into that
statement where you said you started off
by injecting one developer into the
operations team and that kind of started
blossoming that entire Journey for
implementing SRA across across teams
what was the skill set of that developer
and was he fine with moving into
operations did he struggle initially
what were the challenges that you know
you faced around
getting the operations team to accept
that developer as part of the team can
you give me a bit more color over there
please
the developer actually was very happy in
the operations organization because our
operations organization is also very
very close to development so our
operations organization actually doesn't
do traditional operations in a sense
that there are a lot of people like
teams that are just operating Services
because we've got the SRE model now and
that means that the majority of
operations activities they are happening
in the development teams using the SRE
infrastructure so the developer was
actually pretty happy because it was
development work for him so it wasn't
anything kind of uh totally different it
was just the context was different
because the context was about
implementing the SRA infrastructure but
it was development still and that's also
one of the original sort of strength of
SRE that it's all inspired by software
engineering therefore for that developer
it was still the software engineering
World which was important so the
developer started learning about SRE
together with me and we then drove the
transformation by understanding the
features that would be needed in the
infrastructure by understanding the
team's needs so that they would be
willing to use the infrastructure and
that's actually one of the important
points so we didn't force anyone any
team to use the SRE infrastructure so if
a team was happier using something
different then we accepted this and then
moved on to another team which by the
way didn't happen a lot because it was
clear that the SR infrastructure
provides advantages
so that was our journey and I think the
apprehension of developers to
to for example take part in the SRE
infrastructure implementation work would
not be generally there so if a developer
is open to work on infrastructure
instead of for example on some fancy
application development then that would
be still a very interesting development
field for for a development
right I now like to move on to the
approach and if you can help me walk
through the a step-by-step approach to
establishing SRE Foundation you've
expanded on this in your book about
assessment of Readiness achieving
organizational buy-in and you know the
organization structures that need to be
changed so if you can just expand on
that please yeah thank you this is a
very broad question of course because I
wrote an entire book about this let me
give it a try and summarize this as far
as possible when you've got an
organization that's new to SRE that has
never done operations before or they did
operations using some other means which
didn't make the organization happy in
terms of operations and therefore they
want to try SRE then there will be
several significant steps to take one
significant Step At the very beginning
is actually to decide and that already
requires quite some alignment of the
organization
on the one hand it requires alignment
on at different levels of the
organization that means that there needs
to be some interested people in the
teams to give it a try which means some
interested people in the operations
organization some interested people in
the development organization because
they see the potential value of applying
SRE in their organization then another
important bit is that investing into the
SRE infrastructure and investing into
using the Australian infrastructure by
the development teams requires effort
and therefore the leadership of the
organization needs to be aligned on
giving it a try which means the head of
product head of development head of
operations they need to be aligned that
they want to give it a try because it
will require
capacity in the operations teams and in
the development teams
so that alignment needs to be achieved
to some degree so that means that SRE at
some point needs to find its place on
the list of the big initiatives that the
organization undertakes so each
organization will will have a list like
that either it's covered in the in in an
entire portfolio management system or
there's just a list of initiatives that
the organization undertakes and SRE
needs to find its place there it needs
to be there because it requires the
involvement of all the roles in a
software delivery organization because
the software developers will be involved
the product owners will be involved and
the operations Engineers will be
involved therefore in order to make it
happen a certain degree of alignment at
the leadership level will be required as
well then the next step once that is
there is to assess what actually needs
to be done in different parts of the
organization in order to bring the
organization onto SRE so you would need
to assess things like okay so where are
we in terms of the organization in a
sense of what are the formal and
informal leadership structures so how
can we influence teams how can we
Influence People in that particular
organization then in terms of the people
assessment you need to understand how
far away people are from production so
are the developers currently totally
disconnected from production and they
just don't get feedback loops from
production or there are already some
feedback loops and therefore they are
already somewhat closer maybe there is a
difference there between teams maybe one
team is already really operating the
service is actually quite well just not
using SRE means and maybe there are
teams that are really too far away from
production so you need to understand
this
then the next assessments that needs to
be done is technical so what are the
technical means that are available in
order to run something like SRE so do we
have unified logging in the organization
do we actually know which services are
deployed and where say then what is the
current say strategy for alerting what
do we alert upon is the alert fatigue
already now or maybe there are just no
alerts because the development
organization is totally disconnected
from production you need to understand
this and then in terms of culture also
you need to assess the the organization
on the western model which defines
certain aspects of high performance
organization like for example what is
the level of cooperation in the
organization do we have a typical divide
between the operations organization and
the development organization and then
the development organization just throws
their software over the fans to the
operations organization so what is the
degree of cooperation there then you
need to assess things like okay so how
does the organization treat the risks
that are presented that surface
themselves do the messengers get killed
or do the messengers are The Messengers
welcome to present negative news and
then the organization has got good
structures to learn from them and move
forward they need to understanding
General how cohesive the organization
Works in terms of the bridges between
the Departments so how close is the
collaboration between development and
product management how close and is the
incorporation between the the
development and operations and then is
there any cooperation at all between the
product management organization and the
operations organization so you need to
understand these things like that in
order to assess the the culture also
another aspect that would pay into the
culture is how does the organization
deal with failure if there is an outage
so what is done are there any
postmortems is there any blame game game
going on are people fearful to voice
their concerns or the other way around
so that's another aspect of
understanding where the organization is
so then once you've taken that step that
means you've got already a permission to
run the SRE transformation and you also
now have assessed the organization from
various Dimensions so organization
people Tech culture process as well so
what is the process of release of
releasing these options on how
frequently is it released then you need
to you are in a position to craft some
plan of how the SRE transformation could
potentially unfold and I'm deliberately
saying could potentially fold because
this is such a huge socio-technical
change for an organization that has
never done operations using SRE that
you'll never be able to predict what
will happen it all depends on the people
that are in there and there is a lot of
non-determinism that will be going on
during such a transformation so then
once you start I think one of the first
things will need to be to come up with
some minimal SRE infrastructure and then
finding a team that is most willing to
jump on it and then from there you start
snowballing so you then improve the
infrastructure based on the feedback
from the first team then you find the
second best team to put onto the
infrastructure because they are also
interested then you find the third best
team and so on until it becomes a thing
in the organization and there are so
many teams on the infrastructure already
that people are talking about it and
teams are then generally either already
waiting to get on board or even actively
knocking on the door and asking when
they could be on boarded so then with
their onboarding onto this
infrastructure several major things will
happen in the team so one major thing
that will happen is that the definition
of the service level objectives that I
mentioned earlier so the initial
quantification of reliability will
happen and then another major step will
be for each team is to start reacting to
the SLO breaches that will be coming
from the SRE infrastructure that will
start tracking the defined slos in all
deployment environments that are
relevant so generally in all production
deployment environments so one that is
in place then at some point the
formalization of the on-caller rotations
will need to happen and with that then
the the conversation between the product
operations the operations development
and product management need to happen in
order to understand a good split of the
on-call work between the developers and
the operations Engineers so that will be
one of the major points and then at some
point also further things will evolve
and unfold like for example at some
point then the SR infrastructure will be
mature enough to start tracking the
error budget consumption in such a way
that you'll be able to aggregate the
data and present the data to various
stakeholders to the product managers to
the leadership and so on so that
everybody becomes aware of the
reliability of the services and
data-driven decision making about
whether we are investing now in
interreliability versus whether we are
investing now into new features could be
answered in a more day The Driven
approach than before so as you can see
very many steps on the way but the good
thing is that with every small step you
are making a small Improvement that is
also visible and therefore you don't
need to run all the way through to the
end until you start seeing improvements
every little step will mean and a
tangible Improvement yeah quite a few
topics over there that we can deep dive
into later in the session but when I
summarize it I think there are primarily
three foundational steps first is the
alignment to ensure that the SRE
transformation initiative gets into that
prioritized list of initiatives and for
that alignment to happen you need all
stakeholders or majority of stakeholders
to be supporting it because it involves
cost as well as capacity allocated for
the transformation the second
foundational step would be the current
state assessment to understand where is
the organization currently and the third
one once you've got that list into the
prioritized list of initiatives and
you've got the current state assessment
the third foundational step would be to
plan for SRE transformation and once you
you know you have planned it the next
steps that you spoke about starting on
boarding and formalization of on-call
schedule and so on are all
implementation steps that come after the
foundation would that be a correct
summary of that
yeah I think so thanks for summarizing
it succinctly excellent now we'll dig a
bit deeper into each of these and I'd
really be interested in understanding do
you have any example or story on how you
went about getting that alignment and
getting stakeholder support for such a
major transformation initiative
yes definitely for sure so concretely
what we did at team play digital Health
platform was
first of all there were a couple of
people in the organization who are
interested in trying SRE because they
were intrinsically motivated to
on the one hand improve the status quo
but on the other hand also they saw
themselves the potential so they were
eager to explore their potential of SRE
because they saw that that would be a
good fit for what we were doing then a
couple of bottom-up things happened like
so some presentations were there just
informal meetings like lean coffee the
organizations about SRE what that could
mean what that could bring to the
organizational what improvements could
that yield for us and that seeded
already the initial understanding that
there is something out there which could
actually help us with taming the beast
in production so to speak because as I
mentioned earlier actually everything
was growing and that means the number of
users was growing the number of Digital
Services was growing the expectations in
terms of availability of course was
growing and the number of data centers
where the platform was deployed was
growing the number of applications on
the platform was growing everything was
growing and once you are in such a
situation you really need some
Innovative approaches to really tame the
beast in production otherwise it just
you know if you don't have the right
Organization for this it just doesn't
work
so what happened next we started
preparing the leadership team to put SRE
into the portfolio management for the
organization so in the portfolio manager
we've got bigger initiatives that the
organization undertakes and they are all
stack ranked so on the one end it was
important to put SRE onto that list and
the second important thing was to rank
it high enough so that it gets noticed
by the teams so to speak and we'll be
able to allocate some capacity in each
team in order to work on this then we
were talking separately to the head of
development head of operations head of
product and to having conversations
about the issues that we had back then
with operating the platform and how SRE
could help and what we would need in
order to make the first steps there and
then assess whether we are seeing
Improvement and then if we were then we
would be rolling out the sorry more and
more in the organization so once those
leaders who are kind of on board or in a
sense that they also would give it a try
so they would agree to giving it a try
then we managed to bring this into the
portfolio discussion and bring SRE onto
the portfolio list and then ring it high
enough so that enough capacity could be
allocated in teams
so that was the process that we took and
then since then I also advised several
other product lines inside the
organization and showed them the process
and they were also following the process
and reported that yeah that kind of
approach to getting the initial
alignment was helpful so I'd say in
summary the initial alignment is working
both ways it's working bottom up you
need to have some people in the
organization in the teams that are
interested in that kind of thing so you
need to prepare the teams themselves and
you also need to work at the leadership
level so top down so that at some point
some capacity is allocated for the SRE
work and then you can get started I'd
say that combination of bottom up and
top-down is absolutely necessary here
because one without the other doesn't
work so if you don't have anything
prepared in the team yet and then you
get the leadership alignment and the
leaders will come and say okay now you
know work on SRE I don't think that'll
work because then the teams will feel
like they're getting overruled by some
buzzword that they're not aware of and
the managers they just read about it in
some management magazine and that then I
think they might think okay so that's
not fit for purpose because what we're
doing here is is something different and
so on so I think that's not a good idea
and the other way around if you've got
then teams burning will desire to try
SRE because they think that that would
improve the operational capabilities of
the organization but the leadership is
not aligned and doesn't allocate
capacity in one way or another then I
think you can probably get started a
little bit using bottom-up initiatives
but you will not be able to bring it to
a point where it'll become a initiative
and all the teams will be on board and
so on that will not work so you'll be
able to only go so far therefore that
combination is important and that's how
we did it and that's how I saw that also
being a successful approach in other
product lines
Vlad you talked about developers doing
on call usually that's been a very
thorny topic and you know developers
take it very personally because it
impacts their work-life balance do you
have any stories in terms of you know
what were the challenges you faced
around this conversation and how did you
address it and any tips for our
listeners in terms of if they had to
roll it out in that organization well
what could they look at doing and what
learnings do you have for them
Bridges thank you very much for asking
this question and I'm really looking
forward to answering it because I think
that was the most frequently Asked
question by the developers when we
started the SRE transformation so do I
now need to go on call out of hours do I
need to get up at 4am at night to
rectify my service we had lots of
questions like this and I'm happy to
share how we address this what do we
started doing right at the beginning of
SRE transformation was to say look the
whole thing is an experiment we are new
to operating software as a service we
are just trying out whether SRE would be
useful for us in our context therefore
let's only go on call and talk about on
call in the context of the regular
business hours regardless where you are
regardless which time zone your team is
in we are only talking about on call
during business hours and that went down
very well because developers generally
they are eager to try something new and
if it's still within the business hours
doesn't disrupt their life outside of
work then they are generally happy and
looking forward to trying new things
so this is still partly the approach
that we've got right now so now what
we've got is then a development team
that's happy with the on-call hours by
being on call only during the usual
business hours but still that challenges
a development team very profoundly
because a typical development team that
has never done operations before
actually has never had live feedback
loop from production the development
team was working on a release for some
time and then once that release was over
then the development team started
looking into the next release then
worked on that second release for some
time then moved on to the third release
and this is held live in a development
team unfolded now with SRE and on call
suddenly all that changes because you
get a live feedback loop from production
which you need to react to you and the
development team then needs to
reorganize itself in terms of how they
allocate capacity in terms of how they
distribute the knowledge to be effective
at being on call because it does make
sense to put somebody on call who don't
know how to rectify the services then
you need to adapt your planning
procedures capacity allocation
procedures
so lots of aspects are touched upon when
you introduce that live feedback loop
from production into a development team
and also you need to take into account a
particular deployment topology that you
might be having for example in the
template digital Health platform where
you've got six data centers around the
world
now if you are saying that you are on
call then are you on call for all the
six data centers or I won't call for
only one and for how long and so on so
each team needs to deal with those
questions and we took a coaching based
approach and brought that to each team
and discussed that at length in each
team in order to find the setup that's
suitable for them so we don't have hey
you one size fits-all approach that but
each team found over time an approach
that's most appropriate for them that
can also change over time
so that's when it comes to the
operations of the services that the
teams own which means that the scope of
a person that's going on call is just
their service that they own and that's
what we call now bottom-up monitoring
because it just looks at the services in
depth what do we then Learned was
required additionally to be introduced
in order to really provide
a reliable service is the so-called
top-down monitoring the top down
monitoring is system level monitoring
that looks at we call them core
functionalities that cut through all the
services and all the teams
and provide really core functionalities
as the name suggests without which the
platform doesn't work one example of
those core functionalities on our
platform is we are in the healthcare
domain and we connect hospitals to the
cloud and upload data from hospitals
after minimization to the cloud so we've
got a core functionality that is a
function of the data being uploaded to a
data center from all connected hospitals
on average over a Time window
if that data upload throughput drops
significantly then we consider this as a
potential problem with one of the core
functionalities and we look into this so
that combination of top-down monitoring
done by the teams looking at their
services that they own respectively and
then that top-down monitoring of core
functionalities done by a small Central
operations team is the best setup for us
in terms of on-call the developers are
on call 85 means 8 hours a day five days
a week but for core functionalities the
operations team they are responsible to
be on call 24 7.
still here we managed to set up the
follow the sun approach means putting
people into three different time zones
eight hours each so that actually the
people they all operate only during
their business hours but still we ensure
enough on-call coverage and enough on
call depth in order to provide a
reliable platform so that was our answer
to this I think a few points stood out
for me one is it's important to call out
initially that it's an experimental
approach so it's not something which is
set in stone so developers have that
flexibility to feed back and change the
approach if needed I think that provided
them the reassurance so that's very
important and I think your tip about
stressing that developers only need to
support doing business hours that's a
very good point something for us to take
on board for other organizations who
want to implement a survey I think your
answer also nicely transitions us to the
next topic which is around sustainance
so once you've got the foundations in
place what are the key elements for
sustaining and advancing and building on
the foundations of SRE
in order to sustain SRE further in the
organization at some point you would
need to start formalizing the SRE as a
role in the organization and that then
can be either seen as a responsibility
that a developer takes on or it could be
even a full-time SRE role it depends on
the context but you need to deal with
the homilization of the role
number one in the organization then
number two another thing you need to
establish error budget based data-driven
decision making where
you then decide which means prioritize
investments in Feature work versus
investments in reliability work based on
error budget consumption the SRA
infrastructure needs to provide data
which is aggregated and presented
accordingly so that different
stakeholders can engage with the data
and make decisions based on that data
once you've got this then that's another
point that entrenches SRE well in the
inner workings of an organization and
even better if you've got some
organization-wide continuous Improvement
framework and you can put SRE there or
rather just reliability there as a
dimension for continuous Improvement
then that's even better because then you
are part of a bigger continuous
Improvement framework where you inserted
reliability as a dimension which is
measured using Sr means then another
thing that you can do which can be
effective is the setup of an SRE
community of practice where the people
from different teams development
organization operations organization can
meet on a Cadence and then share
experience have lean coffee sessions
have lunch and learn sessions Brown Bag
lunches and so on just to Foster The
Exchange and
you Foster the advancements and the
maturation of the SRE practice over time
thanks Vlad I'd like you to just expand
on the concept of error budget if you
can explain to our listeners what an
error budget is I think it will be
useful to understand the previous answer
and the importance of it definitely
actually I think I should have
introduced that for long ago at the
beginning of the episode but let me do
that now so once you've defined your
service level objectives then the error
budget is calculated automatically based
on the service level objective so let me
take a simple example imagine you set an
availability as a low to say 90 that
means you want your say end point for
example it's at the endpoint level for
example your end points should be
available for 90 that means for example
depending on how you calculate this but
the calculation could be that it's
available in ninety percent of the calls
in a given period of time that means
that your budget for errors is 100 minus
90 10 of the calls and that's your error
budget so the error budget is calculated
automatically based on the SLO if your
SLO is 90 then your error budget is 10
if your SLO is 95 then your error budget
is 5 that means then in the last example
in five percent of the cases if it's an
availability SLO then you are allowed to
be non-available and then you can use
that error budget for things like
deployments because every deployment has
got the potential to chip away a little
bit of the error budget because
deployments can cause failures or just
during a runtime something happens and
you are not available for some time and
then you use your error budget so what
the powerful concept behind the error
budget tracking is that the SRE
infrastructure can tell you whether you
actually used up your error budget but
still didn't use more or whether you
actually used more error budget than you
were granted by the SLO and this is
something that you can then feed into
the decision making by doing proper
aggregations at the service level then
maybe even Team level and so on so you
can do aggregations that are necessary
in order to engage different
stakeholders and that enables you then
to say okay so actually we granted to
this set of services the Aero budget of
five percent but actually they used say
10 that means they're using more error
budget than granted and that means
they're less reliable than dictated by
the slos and that means then as a
consequence we need to invest into
reliability of those Services because we
actually want them to be more reliable
than they currently are right so I guess
it also indicates or error budget is a
budget or the capacity for the
development team to roll out changes
because once you have exhausted that you
know you've got to focus on reliability
stories rather than on enhancements we
have covered a lot of ground year Vlad
but if there was one thing an
engineering manager should remember from
a show what would it be
I think if it's just one thing then at
its core SRE helps you to quantify
reliability and then introduce a process
around tracking whether you are in
compliance with the Quantified
reliability if it's one thing then I'd
say quantify reliability which is
actually a hard problem because usually
the development teams traditionally
they're not very good at quantifying
reliability and SRE provides you with
means to do so and also with processes
that put your organization onto the
continuous Improvement path in terms of
reliability and all that is possible
because the reliability is Quantified
therefore I would say quantify
reliability if it's just one thing that
you want to take away from this podcast
it's a good way to remember it I would
say was there anything we missed that
you would like to mention
British there is so much in each of the
points that we discussed today so I
don't think we have missed anything
grossly but there is so much more to
cover
so there's so much more to learn and I
would encourage everyone to go ahead and
deepen the knowledge in terms of a
Terrain in terms of reliability in
general absolutely and I'll make sure
you have a link to your book in the show
notes so that people can learn more
about rolling out Sr in their own
organizations and learn from your
learnings thank you thank you very much
for having me and it was a pleasure to
be here thank you for coming on the show
it's been a real pleasure this is
prijester Manet for software engineering
radio thank you for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
Channel at SC radio dot slack.com you
can also email us at team sc.radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening